Finding Aid for J. Joseph Herbert Papers, 1880s-1956
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
J. Joseph Herbert Papers 1880s-1956, 1940-1956
Herbert, J. Joseph, 1894-1956.
1 oversize folders
8 linear feet
851466 Aa 2; UAm
Manistique, Michigan, attorney, Republican regent of University of Michigan, and counsel to Michigan State Medical Society. Correspondence and other materials relating to his legal and university career, his interest in the National Music Camp at Interlochen, Michigan, and Republican politics, 1942-1956; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Herbert (donor no. 2989 ) and came to the library in 1959-1960.
The collection is open to research.
J. Joseph Herbert was born in Lafayette, Indiana on August 26, 1894. He attended Lafayette College in Pennsylvania before coming to the University of Michigan where he graduated from the literary college in 1915 and the law school in 1917. He served as an Army officer in World War I then began his law practice in Manistique in 1920. He was a past State Commander of the American Legion (1925-1926), a past president of the Upper Peninsula Development Bureau (1939-1940), and a legal advisor to the Governor Harry Kelly. He was also counsel for the Michigan State Medical Society. In 1939, he was elected to the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan and served there until his defeat in 1955. He died July 27, 1956.
The J. Joseph Herbert collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence, Regents Files, Michigan State Medical Society, Other Activities; and Miscellaneous and personal.
Subjects:
Durfee, Edgar N. (Edgar Noble), 1882-; Herbert, J. Joseph, 1894-1956.; Lawyers--Michigan--Manistique.; Manistique (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan State Medical Society.; National Music Camp.; Republican Party (Mich.); Stoner, Willis Gordon, 1880-; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Herbert, J. Joseph, 1894-1956.; Herbert family.; Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.; McLeod family.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1940-September 1952, 31 folders (Box 1)
  - October 1952-October 1956, 13 folders (Box 2)
- Regents Files
  - Alumni Association (Box 2)
  - Association of Governing Boards (Box 2)
  - Board in Control of Physical Education (Box 2)
  - Board of Governors of the Lawyers Club (Box 2)
  - Budget Committee (Box 2)
  - Buildings and Dormitories (Box 2)
  - Butterfield Theaters, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Bylaws and Rules (Box 2)
  - Bylaws (other universities) (Box 2)
  - Bylaws (other universities) (Box 3)
  - Conference of Governing Board (Box 3)
  - Confidential Data and Reports (Box 3)
  - Financial Reports and Budgets (Box 3)
  - Law School (Box 3)
  - Legislative appropriations (Box 3)
  - Medical School (Box 3)
  - Neuropsychiatric Institute, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Phoenix Project (Box 3)
  - Presidency (Box 3)
  - School of Forestry (Box 3)
  - School of Public Health (Box 3)
  - Student Government (Box 3)
  - Survey Research Center (Box 3)
  - University Club (Box 3)
  - University Hospital (Box 3)
  - University Policy (Box 3)
  - University Record (Box 3)
  - WUOM (Box 3)
  - Workers Education (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Michigan State Medical Society
  - Counsel's Files 1945-1956
    - American Medical Association (Box 3)
    - American Medical Association Legislative Bulletins (Box 3)
    - Annual Session (Box 4)
    - Anti-Trust Litigation (Box 4)
    - Articles for the M.S.M.S. Journal, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Basic Science Act (Box 4)
    - Beaumont Restoration (Box 4)
    - California Physicians Service v. Insurance Commissioner (Box 4)
    - Chippewa-Mackinac County Society (Box 4)
    - Commission on Healing Arts (Box 4)
    - Conference Legal Counsel (Box 4)
    - Constitution and by-laws, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Crippled Children's Commission (Box 4)
    - Federal Lobbying Act (Box 4)
    - Foundation for Post-graduate Medical Education (Box 4)
    - Grand View Hospital et al v. County of Gogebic, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Hospital Licensing Bill (Box 4)
    - Howard, Willard H. (Box 4)
    - Immunization Legislation (Box 4)
    - Income Tax-Withholding Insurance, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Kalamazoo Academy of Medicine (Box 4)
    - Malpractice Insurance (Box 5)
    - Mediation Committees (Box 5)
    - Medical Education (Box 5)
    - Medical Jurisprudence (Box 5)
    - Medical Practice Act (Box 5)
    - Michigan Health Council (Box 5)
    - Michigan Heart Association (Box 5)
    - Michigan State Medical Assistants Society (Box 5)
    - Minnesota Experiment (Box 5)
    - Mutual of Omaha (Box 5)
    - Opinions and Requests, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Opinions of the Attorney General (Box 5)
    - Osteopath and General Healing Arts Legislation (Box 5)
    - Robson Property (Box 5)
    - Senate Bill 6 (Box 5)
    - Simplified Insurance Forms (Box 5)
    - Socialized Medicine (Box 5)
    - Tuberculosis Act Amendment (Box 5)
    - Thomas, Fred W. (Box 5)
    - Unemployment Tax Act (Box 5)
    - Veterans Administration Hospitals (Box 5)
    - Wage Stabilization (Box 5)
    - Wallace-Lindeman Inc. (Box 5)
  - General files
    - Undated 1945-1955, 20 folders (Box 6)
    - 1955-1956, 3 folders (Box 7)
- Other Activities
  - State Bar of Michigan 1940-1947 (Box 7)
  - American Bar Association 1938-1940 (Box 7)
  - Republican politics 1942-1956, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Girlstown 1951-1956, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Interlochen National Music Camp 1943-1956, 5 folders (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous and personal
  - Speeches and Speech Material, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Speeches and Speech Material, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Miscellanea 1940-1960, 7 folders (Box 8)
  - Mrs. Imogene Herbert Correspondence, 1954-1960 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook 1925-1956 (Box 8)
  - Student notebooks with notes of law lectures of Edgar Durfee and Willis Stoner circa 1917, 3 volumes (Box 8)
  - Photographs, 3 folders (Box 8)
    (includes portraits and informal photos of Herbert and his wife; also family photos and photos relating to his regental activities; see also oversize folder)
  - Drawings (Box 8)